XXV

A few days afterwards Felise started early in the morning to meet Martial. She was half an hour before the usual time; she was restless and anxious, and could not wait. There was no definite cause for her anxiety—it was a vague feeling of uneasiness, traceable in a great measure to the unhappy death of Mary. By that sudden loss her confidence in the future had been shaken.

Till some sharp sorrow comes we look forward frankly, and never question the certainty that tomorrow will bring the same settled and pleasant circumstances which surround us today.

Her confidence in the future was shaken. Martial was hers now—but tomorrow?

Mary had only left the house an hour, when under the uncontrollable impulse of her secret unhappiness she leaped into the mill-pool.

Felise could not bear Martial to be away from her; so long as he was near, her heart was at peace; the instant he was gone, her uneasiness returned. She could not wait till the usual time, but started too soon.

There was also the thought that now Martial had given up his farm, in a little while he would leave his house, and would perhaps go from her for months—no one could say for how long.

The brook by which she walked flowed on through the meadow, now with its waters level with the sward, now deep between steep banks where the current had worn away the earth. Sometimes a blackbird rushed out from under a hawthorn-bush at her approach; the blackbird loves the water always, and most of all in the warm August days. Now and again the breeze rustled the green flags, tipped with brown, and the tall reeds in the corner seemed to advance and step towards her as they bowed. Felise walked musing by the brook, dreaming in the sunshine, through the shadow of the willows and alders, by the purple loosestrife lifting its spires almost to her hand, by the green rushes where the furrow came to the stream.

Far, far up in the azure there were thin wisps of white cloud idling motionless in the air, flecks such as a painter might throw from his brush; and between them yet more faint and extended webs of vapour. It was hardly cloud—it was thistledown cloud—so fine, delicate, and vanishing, the eye could scarcely trace the lines and pencilling on the sky.

Less brilliantly white because it passed through these, the sunshine fell softly upon the aftermath—on the short grass; and in the brook, looking down from the high bank, she saw the image of the sun, shorn of his dazzling rays, reflected in the water.

The heat was not so overwhelming, the light not so fiery and white-hot; the breeze which blew at times came almost cool, and the rustling of the flags sounded dreamily. A softness and repose had settled on the aftermath and on the stubble; there was haze in the distance, and the masses of elm foliage were rounded and smooth.

The cawing of the rooks going over scarce disturbed the silence of the morning; there was a tone of complacent rest in their calls to each other. Nothing was quick or suggested haste but the hist-hist of a wood-pigeon’s wings cleaving the air with vehement strokes.

Flags and tall grasses and green things, growing down to the water’s edge and encroaching on the bank, hid the forget-me-nots under their tangled cover.

Once again the shadow was idle on the dial; Time was idle, drowsy in summer indolence.

Away in the stubble women were gleaning, gathering ears of wheat from among the streaked convolvulus and the pale field veronica. A sound of pastoral things stays in the word “gleaning;” yet It is the most aching of labours—stoop, stoop, stoop. They laboured and sought the ears of wheat while the summer was slumbering around them.

Love lingered by the brook and watched the running water, touching the reeds and letting them slip through the fingers, pausing to gather a flower, and then in the act sparing it. Let it bloom; do not injure a flower; let it stay in the sunshine by the running stream.

All things seem possible in the open air.

By the water some part of her old faith returned to her. The voice of the sunshine was hope; in the breeze there was a soothing reassurance; a swallow flew before her, following the winding brook low over the sward, and thought shot forward swifter than he.

There are moments when the earth is so beautiful that sorrow seems a dream. It cannot be—it is not real, this regret; we have fancied it, or surely the sun would not shine, the water sparkle like this. To the beautiful, sadness is unknown—it is not in its sphere; is this why we instinctively cling to loveliness?

He had said that he could not love her; yet by the running water, in the soft light of the cloud-shaded sunshine, she felt that it was not true: he would love her, he must love. Some day he must love her.

So by the stream and through the woodlands Felise came to the old barn, and sat down under the chestnut-tree. A jackdaw flew from it, calling jack-jack-daw as he passed over the ridge of yellow-red tiles. In a minute or two she got up—she had sat down opposite the cavernous space where the doors of the barn had been—and went round the tree and sat down so as to have it between her and the barn. Either there had been some slight scarce perceptible movement of something in the barn, or the shadow had deepened, or her imagination, more nervous than usual, fancied it. Of course it was nothing—she would have laughed at the idea of the barn being haunted; yet she went round and sat down behind the chestnut.

Almost immediately a hand was placed on her shoulder; she started, and, as happens in sudden alarm, her lips parted. Before she could cry out a handkerchief was thrust between her teeth, choking the sound in her throat. A loop of stout cord descended round her shoulders and was drawn tight effectually pinioning her arms. Savage force was used to throw her on the ground, and the cord rapidly wound round and round her body to her ankles till she lay swathed in rope. So swiftly was it done that she was helpless before she recognised Robert Godwin.

He knew her strength; it would have been difficult even for him, powerful as he was, to have mastered her in fair wrestling: at least it would have taken time—there would have been a struggle.

But the sudden gag in her mouth not only prevented her crying out, it seemed for the moment to stop her breath; she was, too, sitting down, a position unfavourable to effort. The loop of rope fastened her arms; she was thrown and bound, at his mercy.

Roughly turning her over and over to wind the cord about her, he had not recked that her beautiful face must touch the earth. Now she lay as he had left her on her back, extended at full length; there were marks where a root had pressed into the soft cheek, and a dry leaf adhered to her forehead. Her hat had fallen off—her head was bare.

From below the shoulder to her ankles she was wrapped in a spiral of rope, preventing all movement of her limbs; she could lift her head, her limbs were powerless.

An undulation—a wave of muscular exertion went along her form; with all her strength she strove to burst the cords. They would not yield; her breast heaved—her torso seemed to enlarge as she inflated her chest, and setting her shoulders firmly, arched her back and lifted herself, suspended between the neck and the feet. Twice the undulation passed along her form—twice she raised herself on her neck and heels, the body suspended between—arched—and with her limbs pressed outwards against her bonds. All the strength of her beautiful torso—all the strength inhaled upon the hills—was put forth in those great efforts; the rope stretched, but would not give way. Then she lay still and looked up at Godwin.

His face, usually so black, was blanched to a ghastly paleness—a paleness behind which the dark and sombre expression still remained. Without a word he rushed inside the barn and brought out Ruy, who had been tethered to the broken plough inside.

The reflex action—the brooding—had done this. It was his duty to punish her.

The evil thought had grown in his mind—all her conduct had strengthened his belief that she was Martial’s mistress.

His unapproachable idol had degraded herself—she must be punished—her beauty must be broken as idols were broken. Not in revenge for her loving another, but because she had destroyed her ideal self. She was guilty of crime against herself, and that beauty which she had debased must be ground out of her face forever with Ruy’s iron hoof.

Her lover’s horse—the horse she had fed and petted; yes, under Ruy’s hoof her beauty should perish. One stamp of that hoof and the lovely mould of her features would become indistinguishable. To kill her was nothing; he did not intend that, but that she should live in her crushed shame.

There could have been no more distinct proof of his insanity than his thinking to break the mould without inflicting death, for Ruy’s weight would press down the very brain.

For this chance he had watched morning after morning; but Martial had come too soon, or she had sat looking towards his place of ambush—some little circumstance had delayed him. It was his or Ruy’s movements in the shadow that Felise had seen.

Holding the bridle, he stood a moment and looked down upon the captive.

One glance of intolerable indignation shot from her eyes; then she lifted her head and looked towards the wood—looking for Martial.

He understood, and drew Ruy forward; the horse hesitated to advance, seeing her on the ground almost under him. At the trampling of his hoofs she turned her head again, and comprehended what Godwin intended to do. Her features flushed—it was the suppression of the cry which her gagged lips endeavoured to utter.

Godwin pulled at the bridle. Ruy came up till his hoof cut the sward within a few inches of her ear, but would not step farther. Godwin struggled with the horse and tugged at the bridle. Ruy drew back; for the third time the man conquered and dragged him to her.

In that moment the undulation passed along her form, and she struggled to roll over—to shield her face, to turn it to the ground. Godwin put his foot upon her chest, and pressing firmly prevented her. Dragging at the bridle he had aroused Ruy’s temper; Ruy jerked his head and would not come. Godwin paused and took out his pocketknife, intending to stab the horse and drive him by sudden pain over her.

His foot pressed heavily on her chest.

She raised her head; she saw a quick something pass through the air; it was in itself invisible, yet something passed; there was a sharp report, and she fainted.

The bullet struck Ruy by the temple; he staggered back, reared, and fell over on his side. By main strength Martial dragged Felise away along the ground, lest the last plunging kicks of the horse should strike her; but Ruy did not turn after he fell—he was dead almost instantly. Robert had rushed from the spot at the sound of the rifle.

The little Lancaster oval-bore from which the shot had been fired lay among the thistles at the edge of the copse where Martial had dropped it. Emerging from the wood as he came to meet Felise, he saw Godwin’s foot upon her breast and the horse angrily jerking at his bridle. A shout died on his lips, and the rifle came up to his shoulder. As Robert took out his knife the tube was levelled, and in another instant the ball would have crashed through his brain. But Martial’s good genius, at the instant his finger felt the trigger, caused him to change his aim from the man to the horse; the tube scarcely moved a quarter of an inch, but that quarter of an inch made the entire difference.

In after-days he shuddered at the recollection that in his anger and fear for Felise he might have shot Godwin; the deed might be justifiable, still it would have been homicide, and a weight on his mind for years. The mere change of his thought—a change effected in the hundredth part of a second—had saved him from this.

He cut the rope; he lifted her head; he called upon her name. His kisses fell fast on her lips, and under those kisses she awoke to the consciousness of a stream of incoherent words full of one meaning—love. Passion poured upon her—a flood of love fell upon her heart. His trembling arms held her to his breast, his eyes swam with tears; she knew that he loved her, and her joy was supreme.

XXVI

Except that the mark lingered on her cheek where the root had pressed against it, and that her limbs shook a little, Felise sustained no injury. The shock and terror, great as it was, was overcome by the happiness which so quickly followed it.

Martial loved her. In his struggle with the water in the dark mill-pool, in his struggle with the stolidity and stupidity which are difficult as fate to overcome—when death drew near him he saw clearly how great and noble, how precious she was, how inestimable her love. Her value was made known to him with that distinctness of mental vision which comes in the last apparent moments of life. The thought that he should lose her was more bitter than death—so bitter, so keen that he thought not of death, but of his loss in it. From that instant he was hers; but yet even then his own peril had not forced him to admit that he himself loved her. He valued her—he did not love her.

But her peril changed all things. Instantly there fell from him the artificial restraints he had cultivated, and his heart burst forth. His passion, so long kept back, overcame him utterly.

In truth, he had loved her from the first. Not only her loveliness, but that indefinable personality which is stronger than beauty had seized upon his mind from the very beginning. Denying it to himself, fighting against it, lleeing from it, still it was there. Her peril forced him to own his passion. The past was utterly gone, and he worshipped her with all the fervour of his heart.

So overcome was he with the violence of his emotion that instead of supporting her, she supported him. Her physical exhaustion disappeared quickly; his moral excitement could not subside. She held his head upon her breast; she soothed him; she whispered gently; her strong arms were about him.

Once again they knew no Time. The shadow of the chestnut-tree swung slowly round; the doves came to the wood from the stubble; a blue kingfisher passed, going to the brook; the gleaners rested in the field.

When at last they moved homewards it was beyond noon; they walked through the woodlands beneath the shade, they stayed beneath the oaks, they lingered at the curves of the brook: the breeze whispered their love in the trees; the murmur of the water sang to them; to the sunshine their love gave a meaning. The swallow flew before, but just above the grass; their hearts were swilter than he to respond to each other’s thought.

At home they had much to tell Mr. Goring of Godwin’s insanity. He could scarcely credit it, because he knew no reason for his madness; paradox as it appears, this is correct—we instinctively search for a reason for madness. While they talked in the little room, the window in which looked out on the garden, there was the sound of wheels, and a carriage stopped at the gate. In a moment Mr. Cornleigh Cornleigh was announced, and immediately afterwards entered; he carried a parcel under his arm.

“Morning, Goring,” he said in his jerky disconnected way, bowing to Felise at the same time very politely. “Fine weather—harvest—eh! Most of the corn got in about here—eh! Happened to be driving along the road—thought I would just call—excuse intrusion.”

Mr. Goring put a chair for him, and the Squire seated himself comfortably, facing Felise.

“The fact is,” continued Cornleigh, aware tliat they were waiting for him to explain, “I’ve some pictures here,” undoing his parcel.

“Fine engravings—first-rate—high art—great masters—raise their aspirations—labourers I mean. Were you at our meeting?”

“I was,” said Martial meaningly.

Cornleigh did not apparently notice the remark.

“Want you to help us,” continued Cornleigh. handing one of the engravings to Mr. Goring. “Distribute them, you know—worthy people; have heard you take great interest—charitable—so on. Really fine works,” turning to Felise. “Just look,” spreading them on the table. Felise could not do less than advance and look at the engravings.

Of all the people in the world Cornleigh Cornleigh, Esq., was the last person Goring would have expected to call upon him. No one could ever quite fathom Cornleigh, but there was an explanation of this move. His political prompter—the family solicitor—a man of much broader knowledge of the world than Godwin, had advised him some time since, in view of the next election, to endeavour to gain over certain opponents by a little cheap attention. Amongst these was Goring. The political prompter understood human nature well. He knew that the bitterest and coarsest opponent is often only an opponent because he has not been noticed; wounded vanity and overwhelming conceit is often at the bottom of it. Let the Squire call, or Letitia, and half the enmity would vanish. He was right in nine out of ten cases; Mr. Goring was the tenth, and the exception. This at least was the pretext Cornleigh put forward to Letitia.

But perhaps Cornleigh, sitting so quiet and demurely looking downwards that day in the justice-room, had seen Felise; perhaps he had made inquiries; perhaps he had seized the first opportunity to call and see her, to speak with her, so opposite as she was to the lady whom the world cheerfully pronounced to be “just the woman for Cornleigh.”

The engravings were really very good; Felise said so.

“Important to raise aspirations, you see,” said Cornleigh. “Textile fabrics” (recurring to his speech), “manufactures, trade—hum—ha—hum—supported by agriculture. Hope you will help us, Miss Goring.”

“Mr. Cornleigh, I think the poor people need something to eat more than they do pictures,” replied Felise.

“Heard you were very charitable,” said Cornleigh. “Here’s sovereign.” laying the coin on the pictures. “Oblige me—give someone you know.” Then turning to Martial: “Sorry you can’t get on—no need to leave—see steward—arrangements can be made about the farm. Really didn’t know myself—anything wrong.”

“I am much obliged,” said Martial, “but I must decline; I have determined to have nothing more to do with farming under present conditions.”

“Mistake somewhere,” said Cornleigh—“mistake—think it over—come and see me—will speak to steward—put it right.”

This in spite of Martial’s speech! It can hardly be supposed that the Squire was really so obtuse as not to have felt the point of the remarks Martial made at the meeting, and yet it was always difficult to tell whether he did or did not understand anything. Perhaps Letitia had begun to be alarmed at the loss of income as farmer after farmer quitted his tenancy, and had deterrnined that Martial should stay as an instance of a landlord’s clemency and conciliation. Doubtless she had been talking to the Squire about it. As was observed at the Maasbury meeting, now the rents are diminishing it is remarkable how the landlord fawns on the tenant.

“I cannot turn back,” said Martial. “Thank you very much, but I have made up my mind.”

“Abner!” cried Felise; “why, there’s Abner!”

He was walking across the garden; she beckoned to him, and he came to the window.

“Why, that’s the man—yesterday before me—police withdrew charge. Sad case. Give him sovereicfn—eh!”—Cornleigh offered a picture and the sovereign on it to the labourer.

“Not from you, Squire,” said Abner. “I can’t take nothing from you.”

At that moment Robert Godwin burst in among them, followed by the village constable. Godwin’s coat was torn and his face scratched, for he had forced his way through the hedges in his frenzied state; he was, too, soaking wet, having waded across the stream. When he rushed from the barn he ran and walked miles in a straight line, regardless of obstacles; presently he came back and got the policeman.

XXVII

They all rose at this sudden interruption.

“Arrest him!” said Godwin, pointing to Martial.

“Arrest! What do you mean?” said Mr. Goring.

“I—I—ha—ha—hum!” said Cornleigh.

“That’s the man—take him! Where’s your handcuffs?” shouted Godwin.

“On what charge?” said Mr. Goring.

“On what charge?” asked Cornleigh, naturally repeating, as he had done for so many years.

“I charge him with attempted murder—he fired at me! come, seize him!”

—Godwin thrust the policeman forward; the constable hesitated and looked towards the magistrate for instructions.

“I charge you with the most brutal assault,” said Martial. “You tried to make the horse trample on Felise”—he held Felise’s arm as if it were necessary to protect her even there, “I say arrest him!” shouted Godwin. “Quick—the handcuffs!”

Martial stepped forward with flushed face, but Mr. Goring intervened and held him back.

“Robert Godwin, leave this house!” he cried sternly.

“Leave the house!” repeated Cornleigh.

“He is a spendthrift rascal!” shouted Godwin, pushing to get past Goring, and so at Martial.

Martial tried to get at the fellow. “Keep them apart!” cried Goring.

“Keep them apart!” cried Cornleigh, seizing Godwin’s right arm, while the constable held his left.

“You ruined your cousins—you have brought the Miss Barnards to ruin! You have wasted your substance—you spendthrift rascal!” screamed the steward.

“Martial—Martial!” cried Felise; “don’t, dear! don’t strike him—he is insane!”

Martial ceased to press towards the intruder, but Godwin, in his ungovernable fury, dragged Cornleigh and the constable by main force past the window. From the window a stern hand seized the steward’s collar—it was Abner. Godwin turned fiercely towards him.

“You be the man as killed my Mary,” said Abner.

“Liar!”

“ ’Twas through you and he” (nodding towards Cornleigh) “as she jumped in the mill-pool. Thank you, miss, for the oak coffin as you give her. Measter Godwin, you knows what you said to Mary in the field once.”

With a great effort Godwin forced himself free from Cornleigh and the constable, upsetting some flowers in the window; he struck wildly at Abner as he passed—Abner drew back and let the blow expend itself—and rushed at Martial. Felise sprang in front of Martial and received a skirting blow on her arm; she cried out. Martial, Mr. Goring, Cornleigh, and the constable together seized the madman.

Yet such was his immense strength that he dragged them to and fro—he swung them to and fro—the table cracked as their weight pressed on it, the partition-wall trembled as they came against it. Felise beckoned Abner—he ran in and helped. At last the paroxysm decreased; the four of them held Godwin somewhat still, but he continued to shout forth accusations at Martial, They pinioned him against the wall; he ground his teeth and foamed at the mouth, his face was black as night, his colourless eyes glared at Felise.

“You gave him the horse as a present,” he panted. “Disgraceful! You gave him Ruy as a present, and he—he—he jilted Rosa Wood. He did—there—he was engaged to her—he jilted her!”

“He did not,” said a voice, and Rosa Wood entered. She had knocked several times, but no one answered, and, hearing voices, she had ventured to enter. “He did not. My father broke off the engagement. It was not Martial.”

“I say arrest him!” shouted Godwin, again struggling.

“You are excited—wait till tomorrow,” said Mr. Goring, hoping to reason with him.

“Wait till tomorrow,” repeated Cornleigh.

“What—you?” cried the steward, as if at last recognising his employer.

“You are excited,” repeated Cornleigh.

“What!” cried Godwin, as if this was too much; that the man he had served so long should turn against and hold him.

“Wait till tomorrow—tomorrow,” repeated Cornleigh.

“Why, he insulted you on the platform at the meeting,” said Godwin.

“Try and be calm,” said Mr. Goring.

“Try and be calm,” repeated Cornleigh.

“Let me go,” said Robert, suddenly ceasing to struggle. They left holding him; he walked out of the room and across the lawn, bareheaded in the sunshine.

“ ’Twas you as killed my Mary!” shouted Abner after him; he did not look back.

“He’ll come to hisself presently,” said the constable; “I’ll just see him home.” He went after the steward.

As the agitation in the room subsided, Rosa felt the necessity of explaining her appearance.

“I had something to say to Martial and you,” she said to Mr. Goring. “But I am glad Mr. Cornleigh is here.”

“I am sorry you found things in such disorder among us,” said Mr. Goring, offering her a chair, but she continued standinof near Felise. She had evidently strung up her resolution, and wished to speak at once.

“Martial!” she said.

“Rosa!” his tone was somewhat constrained.

“It is not true that he wasted the Miss Barnards’ money,” said Rosa, turning a Httle and speaking towards Mr. Goring. “The truth is just the reverse—he straitened his own means for their sake. Martial! Martial!” (she spoke to him by name, but her face was towards Mr. Goring), “I—I did not know till the meeting that you were in such trouble. I—I am very, very sorry—don’t leave the old farm. I will lend you my money—it is four thousand—and you can settle” (she could not say “marry”)—“I mean you can stay. Mr. Cornleigh, you will let him, won’t you?”

“Of course,” said Cornleigh. “I—I have just mentioned the matter. Barnard, think it over.”

“No,” said Martial, “I cannot do it; I cannot go back; I will not submit again.”

“Can be arranged,” said Cornleigh. “Mistake put right, you know; all a mistake.”

“Do take it!” said Rosa. “It is my own—no one can stop me; but no one wishes to, for I have told papa. Do take it! it is four thousand—it is plenty.”

“This is very noble of you,” said Felise. “I hate you!” whispered Rosa aside.

“Oh!” Felise drew back. She understood instantly—a whisper, the sound of which the rest had heard, but had not caught the words, was enough for a woman.

“I cannot take; it, Rosa,” said Martial. “It is too much to thank you for—it is beyond thanks; but I cannot—I would rather work with my hands than return.”

“But you must have it—I shall not be happy unless. There, I have said it—I will write—” her voice faltered a little. “Mr. Goring, will you come with me?” Mr. Goring accompanied her to her carriage, she repeated it to him more fully, and begged him to use his influence with Martial, and not to let him leave the old house. He promised to do his best.

Meantime, Cornleigh was fidgeting with his hat; though he was present. Martial could not quite suppress his feelings, and was perhaps more anxious than absolutely necessary in his inquiries if Felise’s arm was hurt. She assured him it was not. Perhaps Cornleigh did not appreciate these attentions to her.

“Must be going,” he said, rising. “Have engagements. Miss Goring—feel sure I can rely on you to distribute these [the pictures]—worthy people. Good morning [bowing]—most important, you know—raise aspirations—I—I—ha—hum—” and so exeunt.

Rosa had heard Martial’s speech at the meeting in bitter misery; he was leaving his forefathers’ home for lack of the money which she possessed so abundantly. If only he had loved her! Her love for him rose stronger than ever—in his ruin, and now that he loved another—he was dearer than ever. This noble woman—noble notwithstanding occasional pettiness—resolved that anyway he should be happy; and after a tearful interview with her father, she drove over to the Manor House; thence, as Martial was not at home, she conquered her jealousy, and ac tually followed him to Beechknoll.

Anyway he should be happy—even with her. With this money he could marry and stay. The sight of Felise almost staggered her, but she was brave. She could not resist delivering that side-thrust, “I hate you!”—still she adhered to her resolution.

By-and-by the constable came back, just to say (and get a glass of ale) that he had seen Mr. Godwin home; he was quite quiet-like now, and had gone up in his room to do some writing. “He will be hisself again tomorrow.”

XXVIII

The yellow moon rising above the hill cast long shadows of the chestnut-trees, and illuminated a section of the barn through the space where the ereat doors had been. The haze of August seemed to have lingered in the atmosphere after the sun had set, and streaming through it the disk of the moon took a yellowish tint. Thus the harvest colour stayed on into the night; burnt by the sun's heat into the wheat and stubble, as hues are burnt in by the potter's furnace, this hazy yellow remained. There was a faint yellow in the stubble under the moonlight; the dried erass retained a faint hint of it; the broad roof of the barn was yellowish-red.

Over the fields all things appeared dim and indistinct; the haze of day had settled down into the night. At hand the increasing brilliance of the moon — nearly full — lit up each leaf of the chestnut-trees. A star by the zenith, and one or two low down in the south, shone with the peculiar light of summer — they flickered slowly, and at each scintillation seemed nearly gone; their light was not equal to their size, and there were wide plains of the sky without a visible star.

The owl had gone past, and the bats had exhausted the excitement which seizes them at dusk. There was no sound of any living thing; the wind had fallen, and the low murmur of the brook among its green flags did not reach so far. Under the hill the copse was touched with moonlight down the slope of the tree-tops; their recesses were in the deepest shadow. For while the beams of the moon illumine the side towards it — that which immediately receives its rays — they are accompanied with Httle diffused light, and away from the actual impact of the rays there is always a darkness. Each leaf of the chestnut-trees on the side towards the east was brightly lighted, but behind each leaf there was shadow. By day the sunbeams would have gone, as it were, round and under the leaf, and there would have been light everywhere; by night there was a lit-up surface in front, and darkness behind.

Ruy lay as he had fallen, and was stiffening in the moonbeams before the chestnut-tree. Two night-crows were busy upon him; his eyes were already gone.

The crows moved uneasily at the sound of footsteps in the narrow lane, but did not rise till a man emerged from the shadow and came towards the tree. Silently the crows flew away into the dark by the copse; there were dots of white, too, now moving among the thistles by the verge of the wood — these were the white tails of rabbits rushing away to their burrows.

Robert Godwin walked straight to the chestnut-tree, and, pausing on the spot where he had thrown Felise, drew from his pocket one of the old flintlock pistols he had so carefully cleaned. Without a moment's delay, and in the most matter-of-fact manner, he placed the muzzle of the pistol against his breast and touched the trigger. There was a flash as the powder ignited in the pan, but the charge did not explode. At the flash a bird fluttered out from the tree into the night.

Godwin did not hesitate in his fatal purpose because of this accidental reprieve from his own violence. He opened the pan and poured fresh gunpowder into it from some which he carried in a screw of newspaper in his waistcoat-pocket. With a pin he cleaned the touch-hole, and then patiently thrust the grains of powder as well as he could into the aperture, in order that the flame might next time communicate with the charge.

Some time since he had purchased two ounces of loose gunpowder at an ironmonger's in Maasbury — cheap powder, such as is sold for birdkeepers" guns; he would not go to the expense of Curtis and Harvey's diamond-grain. He did not quite know when he bought it whether it was to be used against himself or Martial, or against both.

When he thought he had primed the pistol he closed the pan, again put the. muzzle to his breast, and pulled the trigger. The bullet entered his heart and he fell dead; his face struck a bunch of yellow fungi growing in the grass, and lay still there.

XXIX

He had not stayed to look at the stars, or to consider before his deed in the shadow of the chestnut tree. His purpose was death, and he had walked to it straight without looking to the rieht or to the left. The dim outline of the hills was nothinir to him; he had seen in the hills nothing but mounds of chalk in life, why gaze at them on the eve of death? In the years of his life he had never lifted his eyes to the stars except to see if the sky was clear from cloud.

There was no meaning to him in the stars, or in the hills, or in the sea whose long low surge beat the beach beyond them. The idea of immortality had never been orrasped, nor the idea of anything beyond the material and tangible. It is questionable whether he had ever grasped even the idea of a gas, as it is invisible—that which he could see and touch was all that Godwin knew.

There are many who repeat words of the like import freely, and have no conception of their meaning any more than veritable parrots.

Godwin was true to himself, and repeated no words the import of which he did not understand.

He had been insane when he attacked Felise; he had been insane when he struggled so violently in the room at Beechknoll; but he was not insane at the moment of his death.

The fit had passed from him, and he saw things clearly. As thunder dispels the heaviness of the atmosphere, so the sultry gloom of his brain had been dispelled by that vehement passage of hate and personal violence. His brooding burst out in uncontrollable action, and immediately afterwards his mind was relieved.

He knew then that the last nine years of his life had been in vain; that he might as well have been dead those nine years; that he might as well have been dead from the very moment he beheld her, and his unattainable love began.

How powerful, and yet how uncontrollable by ourselves, is the influence of our life upon the lives of others! To Robert Godwin the life—the mere existence of Felise had been a terrible fate. For aught you can tell, your existence may be a fate to another—another’s to you.

From that instant he might as well have been dead, for his existence since had merely been an increasing madness of desire for the unattainable.

If anyone could have argued with him and pointed out that however great his trouble now, in time—slow time—the trouble would wear away; in time—slow time—the memory itself would become dull and the vivid impressions fade; that he would come to live again, and to go about his duties as of old—then Robert Godwin would have laughed in derision.

He did not want his trouble to wear away, nor to return to his former self. So deep and so organic was the change produced by inalienable passion that his former condition before it commenced, even in his unhappiness, appeared to him worthless. He would not have returned to it if he could have done so.

The moment he came to himself and saw how hopeless his life had been these nine years past, he was dead. The act had not been committed, but he was dead of intent. He saw that, according to the strict logic of his nature, he should have slain himself nine years since.

The absence of imagination prevented him from amusing himself with possibilities of another life in another land, of finding a face some day in another country which might in part be to him as this one had been. This absence of imagination prevented him from seeing anything that was not immediately before him; it slew him, but it rendered him faithful to his passion and to himself in his death.

His death atoned for nothing. The manner and the time of it were absolutely and purely selfish. He died for himself and for no other.

It rendered no reparation—even imaginary or sentimental—for poor Mary Shaw; it had no appearance even of sacrifice for the sake of those whom he had so harshly treated; there was no redeeming regret. There was no nobility, however mistaken, nor elevation in it; with no thought of any other but himself he died, and it seemed to be no matter to the earth any more than the death of the horse beside which he lay.

By-and-by the night-crows returned to the carcase of the horse in the moonbeams before the chestnut-tree.

Godwin had left his papers in perfect order, notwithstanding the fact that he had done no pen-work for some time. They were all sorted and filed, and a memorandum had been drawn up stating where the money in hand was to be found, and directing the person who should be deputed for the purpose how to make up the accounts from the sorted papers. Not one sixpence of Cornleigh Cornleigh’s money was missing, so faithful a servant had he had. The mechanical precision with which this had been done was characteristic of the man.

This was the writing which he had gone upstairs to do, as the constable said, quite quiet and like a lamb. It had occupied him—with intervals of thouerht—till dusk. He sat awhile after it was finished, then took one of the pistols from the attic where he had accidentally found them, and walked to the barn. As for the act, it scarcely took three minutes till he was stretched lifeless with his face crushing the yellow fungi.

The silence about the chestnuts and the barn was unbroken till in the morning the rooks awoke in the wood on the hill and flew out over the fields.

Godwin’s will had been drawn up years before; it left his property to his sister, with the strictest proviso that in case of her marriage the money should devolve upon her children. Beyond receiving the interest, her power over it was little. His estate, real and personal, was estimated at about twenty thousand pounds; an immense sum to be accumulated under such conditions, for sums must be measured by circumstances. That which is a trifle to the financial monarchs of London is a vast amount in the country. What grinding self-denial, what harsh economy to himself and others that twenty thousand pounds represented!

When it became known in the morning that Godwin had destroyed himself, Mr. Goring and Martial reproached themselves for not at least having endeavoured to obtain his arrest. The circumstances of the assault on Felise, if sworn to before a magistrate, would have secured his detention, and might thus have saved his life.

That they should have thought thus, again shows how little we understand even those who live close to us, and whose actions appear to give a clue to their minds. Had Robert Godwin been confined in a cell for a month, or six months, it would not have altered his purpose. At the first opportunity he would have carried out his determination. Martial had been eager to bring him to answer for his conduct, but Felise had begged so hard that if possible the matter might not be made public, he had submitted.

Artistically speaking, Robert Godwin ought not to have committed suicide; he should have removed himself in some other way—he might have gone off to America, or disappeared. He rather spoils the narrative, giving a cold deadly sensation to the finale; but he really could not help it—it was his nature.

Martial received a notification through Cornleigh’s solicitor, that if he would reconsider his resolution matters could be arranged for him. Either the Squire was advised to make friends with the enemy, or it was feared that Martial’s example might spread, and others leave. Too many had gone already. There seemed the greatest reluctance to part with a tenant, a state of sentiment which to the older farmers contrasted singularly with the treatment they had received a very few years ago.

Rosa wrote him a letter repeating her noble offer; but despite these persuasions Martial remained unmoved, and took steps to leave the old place. Generous as Rosa’s offer was, he could not endure the idea of marrying with the aid of her money. Nothing could induce him to accept it; Rosa had not even this mournful pleasure.

What he should do when the stock was sold, and he stepped for the last time over the threshold of the house his forefathers had dwelt in, Martial had but the vaguest idea. While he was considering one plan and another the thing was settled for him.

A report of his speech at the Maasbury meeting got into the hands of his former London friends, who were so delighted with his independent spirit and opinions—particularly as these chanced to fit their own—that they sent for him to town. The former understanding was renewed, and the old quarrel forgotten. As the years had stolen on, the old folk too began to consider the end; they had no other natural heir but Martial, and with him personally had never disagreed.

An allowance—a very handsome one—was offered to him; but he refused to accept it unless employed in some way. The upshot was he was engaged in the design department of the great firm of marine engineers in which his friends were the principals. Here his ingenious turn of mind soon found scope. His time was really his own, and he was naturally often at Beechknoll. His friends have given him to understand that at the next election, if it can be arranged, he will be put forward to contest Maasbury independently.

Before the golden tints had faded from the trees, Felise and Martial were married.

XXX

Out of the dusk which lingered on the earth, while in the sky the light was approaching, a lark sprang up and, soaring above the darkness, sang by Beechknoll. It was a very early morning in May, and Felise, in her dressing-gown, had stolen quietly to the window, and sat there watching the dawn. Martial was sleeping. They had come down for awhile to be with Mr., Goring, who was lonely even among his trees. The man slept; the woman, wakeful in her happiness, stole to the window where she had so often sat of old time.

Upon the ground there lay a stratum of darkness which seemed scarcely to rise so high as the eaves—a darkness visible Hke a mist, thickening in the corners and by the trees. Through this the lark soaring sang in the clear air above.

Afar along the ridge of the hills there was a white light—the dawn—which imperceptibly rushed rapidly through the atmosphere, not only rising to the zenith but spreading horizontally over the fields. The trees that were towards the east began to have beneath them the dim outline of their own shadow on the grass. Already these dim outlines of masses of foliage shadowed on the sward were visible through the sinking stratum of darkness.

Another lark sang at a distance, and then a third; their notes fell with the last rays of the stars. So long as the night-blue tint of the sky continued the stars shone; as the dawn-beams shot upwards and increased in brightness this night-blue tint began to change, and with it the stars retired into the depths of space. There was a gleam like dew on the pearls lying by the mirror; Martial had redeemed them, and she had worn them the previous evening.

In a moment, as it seemed to Felise, the darkness on the ground vanished, and all things appeared distinct and clear. Really the change had been gradually advancing—in appearance it seemed effected almost suddenly.

Immediately a thrush commenced to call in the thickets that had been planted so abundantly about the house, a second answered; a blackbird called; then, as if at a signal, the whole choir began to sing. There was a score of them, thrushes and blackbirds; all started at once; their chorus burst upon the dawn.

The stars were gone, and the deep azure of the morning filled the sky. By the ridge of the hill the white light shone brightly; above it a purple mingled luminously with the blue; towards the zenith the loveliness of the colour is not to be written.

The man slept, but the woman, wakeful in happiness, sat by the window. The dawn shone on her face, and upon the beautiful golden hair drooping to her knees. Her hands were folded, the same attitude in great happiness as in inconsolable sorrow; the dawn glistened upon the tears in her eyes.

Her feeling was perhaps the deeper because he slept, because she was alone and yet with him. She did not strive, womanlike, to mould her feelings to his mood—she gave way to her own.

Her joy was so great because her life was fulfilled. So soon in the springtime of youth her life was fulfilled; there was nothing more beyond to strive or hope for. It was the joy of intense rest in possession.

The man knows no such feeling. To him the joy of existence is in pursuit and conquest; while he is succeeding, while pursuing and gaining in pursuit he rejoices—the mere possession is little or nothing. The more active his days—the greater his scheme of the future—so much the more he loves the woman he has chosen.

But the woman has no future. Her all is here. In possession is everything; in that her life is fulfilled.

As the miser gloats over his gold, not for what it will purchase, but for its own sake, so the woman gloats over possession, not for any future success, but because he is hers now.

Of what the day might bring forth she thought nothing, whether it should be profit or failure, so long only as he was there. Of what the years might have in store, wealth or poverty, concerned her nothing so long as he was with her.

A pure rest had come to her life.

Except to love and to love fulfilled, and then only to woman, is such rest ever given. For the heart, and the hand, and the mind of a man are forever driving onwards, and no profundity of rest ever comes to his inmost consciousness. At dawn he looks forward to the noonday.

So that true and restful happiness is for woman only, though it is given to her by man.

A golden breath came up among the bright whiteness of the light over the ridge of the hill; there were scarlet streaks, the lips of the morning. In the glorious beauty of the sunrise her heart brimmed to the full of love.

“Felise.”

Her answer was a kiss amid the dew of loving tears.

XVIII

■|NTERING the garden by a side- path, Felise heard two voices in ^^ loud altercation, or rather one voice stridently asserting itself over the other, and she paused where she could see the disputants through the open window.

Goring in the whitest of white shirt-sleeves — ^just as he had left his spade — was standing by the mantelpiece, resting his firm chin on his hand, and steadfasdy regarding the steward. His high forehead, pardy bald, and flecked at the temples with grey among the brown of his hair, expressed calm intellect reposing in itself. Not the nervous, eager brain which seeks preferment and must thrust

Itself to the front; the intellect which reposes and reflects.

There was almost too much mind for action behind that noble forehead; it was the thinker, not the doer. The clear, steel-blue eyes under their thick eyebrows, the set mouth and the firm chin, at the same time indicated an immovable will; a man who would have his way without the least outward noise or ostentation. His strong frame — a trifle bowed, as those of men usually are who work with their hands for pleasure or profit — and great breadth were fully exposed by his negligent costume; his brawny throat, indeed, was visible. ' If only papa would work among men instead of among trees, what a leader he would be !' thought Felise.

Mr. Godwin, with his hat on (not an in- tentional rudeness), stood by the table on which he struck his fist, clad in dark brown and wearing gaiters. He was of full average height, stout, and strongly built; he appeared

capable of exKgooiaL ^^i'JTrrr^ ri-^ nsi on the tabie "irss irmFx i:£ l piei^ of oak that h^^' besE e2:x35e£ iZ rbe 'R^t.er to the action of iiie -wsaciKr. His fii:?r was neither ruddy, hroin^ nvc vjarJjL. bjt a mixture of the three; i vs rjidfr fron a fulness of blood; 31 ursi itittj fr::c: T'-:nd and rain : it was Kaci fr:m: sir. H^ face might have been est it iiruize, 50 reniarkable was the appeaisnax: rf !i5crfib>>d.

His fescira -w^r' r^alar, and, except that the deeij w^rt somewhat too full, might even tare Etta safd to be handsome, but they were asc m a set expression; his mouth — t&fe worst feature, being without cun-e— did niut smile; his brow had a lino constantly tiiere. This fixidity, and the ex- tremely weather-beaten hue of his complexion, seemed to announce a concentration of cha- racter that made most people shrink fVoni him. Mr. Goring was brown from the sun. yet beside Godwin he looked fair.

Godwin's voice was loud; he hurled ^''''

words and shut his lips tight immediately; but his language was correct, for he was well educated. Possibly his exceptionally hardy nature had something to do with his pitiless character. A man with thousands in his pocket, but who was content with a coarse fare of bread and bacon, or even bread and cheese, was not likely to feel much senti- mental sympathy for weaker beings.

His family had all been alike; 'hard as crab-apples ' was the saying of the country- side.

Every tenant upon the estate spoke in the highest terms of Mr. Godwin to his neighbour. At the public dinners Mr. God- win was mentioned with the deepest respect. ' A shrewd, first-rate man, Godwin; knows his business; a good fellow, too, at bottom.' Alone, in private, there was not a man who did not hate him; but not a man would have dared to admit as much even to his wife.

In Mr. Goring's calm glance there was

perhaps some little admixture of amused disdain. Godwin glared with his colourless grey eyes, the angrier because he could not impress the person he was attacking. ' You cannot show a scrap of paper/ Felise heard Godwin saying. ' Tm certain there is no such deed. You have no more right to fish than you have to give that rascally labourer of yours more money than anyone else.' ' I believe/ said Mr. Goring, 'that the law permits me to pay what wages I please/ ' It does not permit you to trespass and to leave gates open, so that cattle stray and do damage. You'll have to pay for it, Goring — mark my words! What right has she to trample down the grass and do every species of mischief .-^ Even if you do possess, or claim to possess a right to fish, it does not extend to her.' ' Was it me, then ?' asked Felise suddenly, coming to the window. ' You are the culprit/ laughed her uncle.

I90 THE DEWY MORN. ' Why, you have the rod in your hand — you're caught/

Godwin looked at her, and instinctively removed his hat. He growled something in his throat. He did not speak, but he had the grace to be silent. ' You are accused of poaching, trespassing, and doing every species of mischief,' said Mr. Goring. ' Come in and defend your- self.'

Felise smiled, and went round the hoiise to the front door; but on turning the corner started, became pale, flushed again, and then stepped quickly towards a horse Abner had care of. It was Ruy — Martial's horse.

Was /^e here, then ?

She stroked Ruy's neck, looked in'side the hall, returned, stroked him again; in her agitation she scarce knew what to do, or say, or think. ' Is Mr. Barnard here ?' she said at last. ' No, miss,' replied Abner. ' But— but '

191 ' Mr. Godwin came on him/ said the man.

Godwin riding Martial's favourite — how was this ? Felise instantly felt that there was something wrong, and Godwin's dark face appearing at that moment in the hall seemed sinister to her. His pale grey eyes — colourless like water — shone in the shadow of the doorway. She could not ask him any questions, but she did not withdraw her hand from Ruy's neck. The horse rubbed his face against her shoulder. ' I've just bought him,' said Godwin, soften- ing his voice as much as he could. ' Do you like him ?' ' Yes.'

He began to gather the bridle in his hand, taking it from Abner. Godwin was so near her that her dress touched him. She felt his direct glance beating upon her, as the hard sun beats on an exposed rock. There was no cessation in his glance.

She remembered the remark of the

cottager that Barnard was not rich, that young blood spent money. Could it be that Martial was in difficulty ? How else came he to part with his horse ? Her heart quailed; quick sympathy confused her. She did not move aside that Godwin might mount, but stood by Ruy.

Godwin s colourless eyes were bent un- swervingly upon her face; he had the bridle in his hand, but he was in no haste.

In her agitation Felise did nothing but stroke Ruy, who was growing impatient for his manger — so affection is wasted upon those whose sole thought is provender. ' I am afraid I gave too much for him,' said Godwin.

Mr. Goring smiled; the idea of Godwin giving too much for anything was good.

Felise was running over in her mind everything she could think of that would be likely to draw out the truth, yet without betraying her interest in Barnard. ^ Have you had him long ?' she asked.

193 ' No, only a week or two/ ' From whom did you buy him ?' — as if she did not know. ' Barnard of Manor House/ ' Did you give much ?' ' Seventy pounds.' ' Why did he want to sell ?' ' Wanted the money; but I dare say there's something wrong with the horse. I shan't find it out for a month or two — Barnard's too sharp for me.'

Mr. Goring, in the porch, smiled sarcas- tically. If Godwin gave a man the character of sharpness, it went without asking that he was anything but shrewd at such matters as a horse-deal.

Still stroking Ruy — her dress rustling against Godwin, Felise for the second time; delayed the impatient horse; just as she had on the hills one morning. ' Mr. Godwin wants to mount/ said Goring at last. ' I forgot,' said Felise, and moved away; VOL. I. 13

the steward, however, did not seem in any- great hurry. He got up leisurely enough, but reined Ruy with so powerful a hand that the horse stood quiet, and Felise touched his neck once more. 'Will you come over and see us?' said Godwin. ' My sister would be very pleased if you would; the meadows are dry now, and the path easy.' ' I will come,' said Felise, to her uncle's astonishment. ' Soon r ■ To-morrow morning.'

Then she looked up at Godwin's cast- bronze face, and asked in the most matter-of- fact tone she could assume : ' Why did Barnard sell — why did he want money ?' ' Because he's a fool,' said Godwin rudely. She flushed — he thought it was because of his rudeness. ' Beg pardon,' he said. ' You will be sure to come to-morrow morning Y

195 ' I will;

Still Godwin lingered, Ruy fidgeted; Goring wished to go to his garden-work, but Godwin did not start. A moment passed without a word being spoken, when Felise slightly bowed and went in; Godwin immediately rode off without a word. 'Are you really going to visit them.'^' asked Mr. Goring. ' Yes, papa; unless you object.' ' No, I don't object — still, you know the man's character.' ' That he is a tyrant, yes; but I am going to see Ruy.' 'Ruy?' ' Oh, I mean the horse. I heard his name just now. He is a beautiful horse, isn't he?'

XIX

as it best to have a strong imagina- tion, or to be entirely without it ? An imaginative mind creates for itself a beautiful world; but upon entering into practical life, at every step, first one and then another portion of the structure is shattered till the entire fabric falls to pieces. Dust under foot and bitterness to the taste are all that remain; a void heart, a hopeless future, a weary present. The commonplace crushes the ideal as a cannon-ball might a statue.

The world, therefore, has long since decided that the imaginative is to be avoided. Have nothing to do with books, pictures.

sculpture, with thought or dream. Above all things be practical.

Those who do not possess an imagination are clearly the gainers in this life; horses, carriages, money, expensive wines, or, if they prefer it, the solid applause of well-to-do folk, are given to them. The imaginative dream of flowers, but the practical possess a garden. The infinite superiority of the non- imaginative is established.

Robert Godwin had never any diffic\dty in choosing between these two courses — the imaginative and the practical — because he had not even imagination enough to se^ that there were two courses. By nature he was absolutely devoid of imagination. He took things as he saw them, and the idea of there being anything beyond never occurred to

him.

There were the hills visible from his win: dow; he knew by experience that hills were steep, and that a horse had to pull against the collar to draw him over them. The

higher they were the thinner the soil, the smaller the crops, and the less rent to be obtained. Occasionally he glanced at them to see if the descending or ascending mist, the clearness or dimness of outline, promised rain or sunshine — and so much for the hills. This practical knowledge completed his con- cern in these mounds of chalk.

The depth of the rich blue sky, the sweep of the clouds, the sunrise, the colours of sun- set, the stars so clear seen at an altitude — these mere imaginative things were invisible to him altogether. He simply did not see them, any more than if a thick curtain had been drawn before his eyes.

The thoughts which flow from the contem- plation of the azure, the noble hope of sunrise, the god-like promise of the stars, were to him non-existent; as he could not see the things that suggested the thought, so his mind was blind to the thought itself.

Yet further, that scarce definable culture — that idea which exists in the heart and soul

independent of outward appearances — the sense of a beautiful inner life — so delicate a music was soundless to his ears.

The ground was solid under his feet ,- the sky afar off a mere translucent roof; the sun around ball of heat, never seen unless he chanced to be driving westwards towards sunset. He measured trees, and put a red mark against those to be felled, so many every year; they were timber — wood; they were hard, oak some of them; he could tell the cubical contents, and how many feet of planking they would saw up into. The shape of the oak, the shadow, the birds who came to it, all its varied associations— its dream — had no meaning to him. Sometimes he saw the sea, its green plain, from the higher ground; but it did not attract him to the shore.

Through the woods in spring-time his feet waded among pools, broad lakes of azure- purple, acres upon acres of blue-bells, so crowded they could not swing; he crushed

the tender anemone; he passed the white June rose.

Robert Godwin never walked by the sea, nor gathered a flower.

The old books which had accumulated in the house of his forefathers remained upon the shelves untouched. Since his school- days, when it was compulsory, he had never opened any other book than the almanack. .

He handled cattle and sheep, he inspected horses, he visited men at plough, at harrow, at harvest, at building, at sawing, smith's work, every kind of labour. He attended markets and fairs, he drove and rode to and fro; he kept his accounts; he looked to every detail of the estate and of his own farm. He was always in action; when he returned from a long day's round, so soon as he alighted he walked briskly down into the garden to see if the gardener had fulfilled a full day's task.

Robert Godwin drove men as cattle are never driven. For cattle are let linger by

the roadside that they may crop the clover which likes to grow in trodden places; cattle are permitted to drink at the pond, and to rest in the shade of the elm-trees. The evening comes and they are turned into a field to graze, and chew the cud, and con- sider, as it were, till the morning.

No man rested that Robert Godwin could get at to drive. His own farm labourers, the men who did the estate work, the wood- cutters, the drain-diggers, the masons and smiths, the very messengers to and fro the Squire's house and his farm — he drove them all. He would waylay tjie rural postman at six in the morning, and bully him for not coming at half-past five : what business had he to waste time taking a draught of milk at the farmhouse yonder? He should be re- ported. Robert Godwin stood at the stile and shouted to the children, and threatened them with the stick if they did not hasten on to school.

Yet when Robert Godwin's back was

turned and the hedge had hidden him from view, the ploughman relaxed his hold on the stilts of his plough, and the team stayed as he listened to the peaceful caw of the rooks. But Godwin's back was never turned upon himself. He drove himself for ever. He was always up at six, often at five; from then till dusk he moved to and fro his own farm, and the estate he managed; after dusk a cheap candle was lit for him, and he worked at his accounts till bedtime. He never listened to the caw, caw of the rooks.

Reading by the open window of a sunny day, when the mind for a moment pauses from its dwelling on the page, and the glance goes out into the light, it is very pleasant to hear them — these peaceful rooks caw, caw- ing over to their favourite furrows. Doubt- less you have heard them and rested. Robert Godwin never heard them.

Incessant physical occupation was a neces- sity of his existence. But surely there must have been times when, his hands being still

and his frame reposing in the early evening, 'between the lights/ his mind roamed in reverie, when fancy bore sway, when a dream or thought came to him ?

No. When his hands were still and his frame reposed, his mind was simply vacant, like that of a horse looking from his stable- door, or a dog by his kennel. He saw the wall, or the fireplace, nothing more. His mind was simply quiescent — vacant — like a mirror turned face downwards, as old country- folk place them on the bed in a storm of thunder and lightning.

In such a position the glass reflects nothing, and so when his hands were still Godwin's mind reflected nothing. It did not work within itself. Thus it was that on lying down at bedtime he fell instantly asleep, sound, undisturbed, complete, like an animal's. No long train of aerial fancies passed through his mind; that organ, like a muscle unemployed, fell into perfect repose.

This incessant work was not persevered in

as a ' religion,' such as it is the fashion nowa- days to ' dignify ' toil for the benefit of those who own factories. Nor was it the restless energy of a great genius, for Godwin had no ambition, and to drive nails in a carpenter's shop would have contented him as well as to lead the army at Pharsalia, Nor was it nervous restlessness; he was quite without nerves. It was his nature.

Just as rooks fly because they are rooks, so Godwin worked because he was Godwin, worked and accumulated money, and drove himself, and every human being with whom he came into the smallest contact, and knew no more rest or fatigue than the old mill-wheel.

His forefathers had had money; it was a family, a hereditary trait — this faculty for accumulation. Robert got together more, and it was whispered that he had lent a large sum to the Squire. Certainly his will was law on the Cornleigh estate; it was no use appealing to the Squire, who merely referred applicants back to his steward.

THE DEWY morn: 205

There could not have been a more faithful steward. There was not a halfpenny wasted on that property, not the value of a rusty nail. Economy, rigid control, perfect ac- counts; every shilling brought to the board. Everything organized and in order; no con- fusion, no uncertainty. Above all, no weak paltering with tenants who had had losses, or suffered from illness or infirmity; no feeble yielding to the entreaties of the widow, or the fatherless children, or the unfortunate. The same rigid rule was applied unfalteringly to all alike, so that there could be no favouritism : ' Pay or go.'

The steward allowed no time, consented to no compromise. ' Pay or go.' Three omnipotent words, which brought to the Squire's pockets an unfailing supply of gold twice a year.

Some did, indeed, say that the reputation thereby acquired prevented tenants with large capital from applying when farms were vacant; they would rather go farther and

have more freedom and kindliness of treat- ment. However that might be, for the present, at all events, the Godwin rule was a success.

It was thought that the succession of bad seasons must necessitate a relaxation of this iron government, but fortune sometimes favours the hardest natures, and in this case favoured Robert Godwin. By a piece of good luck that neighbourhood did not suffer so severely at first as many districts; the crops were below the average, but not so seriously; some little allowance had to be made, but not much; the tenants certainly lost money, yet they could not make out a sufficiently pressing case to obtain much reduction of rent. Of late there had been more serious complaint. No appreciable difference was caused in the Godwin govern- ment.

He was ever on the alert, just the same, to detect the least infringement of the strict letter of the agreement; ever ready with

objections if any expenditure was applied for; always watching for an opportunity to assert the authority of his master.

A labourer began to build a hut on waste ground by the wayside. Godwin had the materials carted away, as he had commenced without permission from the lord of the manor. A cottager had made a garden in a hedge, leaving enough of the fence each side to prevent cattle straying; he worked on the estate, but Godwin spied out the encroach- ment and had quickset thorns planted among the potatoes.

The thatched roofs of the cottages in one of the hamlets were rotten, and let the rain through; the poor inhabitants begged for repairs. Nothing of the sort : they could buy straw and repair the roofs if they wished; if not, the wet might drip on their beds.

Enclosure of the common had already begun when Mr. Goring came forward and contested the right of Cornleigh Cornleigh, Esq., to enclose. Godwin blustered and

thundered; letters were written on blue paper; but public opinion had been drawn to the question, emissaries from powerful societies appeared on the scene, and the scheme was let drop.

Some day, perhaps, Mr. Goring would leave. These objectors have never much status or stability. They are not fixed like great hereditary owners. The Pope is dead — long live the Pope ! The interests of here- ditar)' estates are handed on generation after generation, much like the will of Peter the Great; but objectors, such as Mr. Goring, usually disappear in a few years. The hand that repairs the embankment once withdrawn, the sea soon rushes in.

Godwin was ceaselessly on the alert to extend the authority of his employer. Foot- paths were stopped, and odd corners of waste ground enclosed with stone walls costing thrice the value of the land, in order that no one might 'squat' and presently assert a right to a few square yards of their own country.

These proceedings were by no means con- fined to the outlying agricultural places, where the well-to-do people were almost all tenants, and the remainder poor and without organization. Robert Godwin attacked the town with equal zest and equal success. The Cornleigh Cornleigh property included a considerable part of the town, and his ' rights ' extended more or less over the rest.

Except by long and costly legal process it was impossible to tell where those ' rights ' really began or ended. The steward made the fullest use of this uncertainty. Old by- ways and paths were blocked, cprners en- closed, possession asserted and taken, and not a voice was raised. The whole town was straitened, and a band as it were drawn tight about it so that it could scarce breathe.

The park was closed, though the inhabitants had used it for a hundred years as a recrea- tion ground, and had undoubted claims to roads across it. Not a voice was raised^

VOL. I. 14

Old inhabitants retained a respect for ' the family/ and would not oppose its will. Tradespeople wished to enjoy its custom and patronage, though, as a matter of fact, they got neither, as ' the family ' bought all they required in London; still they did not like to shut the door in their own faces. There were not enough shoemakers in Maas- bury.

Long since there had been a glove in- dustry in the surrounding villages — an in- dustry at which the poor folk worked in their own cottages. For the most part it had dis- appeared, yet to this day the magistrates could distinguish the hamlets where it had once flourished by the records in their books. To this day half the cases brought before them came from these hamlets.

Your artisan who works at home — ^your cottage glovemaker, or shoemaker — is a terrible radical, a fearful character, a fre- quenter of taverns, a fisticuff fellow, and above all things a contemner of authority.

He will get into trouble for no other purpose than to show his despite of authority. His descendants had it in their blood, and still continued to exhibit the same disposition. But the industry had died out, and there were no shoemakers to speak of in Maasbury town. Consequently Mr. Godwin ruled as he chose.

The result was that the property was trimmed, walled, enclosed, and improved in every possible manner. Had it been set out to sale, the auctioneer could have honestly laid stress on the singular completeness of the estate. It was in perfect order. The • family ' reaped that advantage.

A breathless hatred of Robert Godwin prevailed from north to south, east to west, of that broad stretch of land. From the tenant of a thousand acres, and the wealthy tradesman (like Rosa's father) down to the miserable old woman in her shanty, living on tea and soaked bread, the hatred of Robert Godwin was universal.

The well-to-do exhibited this feeling by- asking him to every entertainment they gave — invitations seldom accepted, for Godwin was a solitary man — by publicly praising him at every meeting, by treating him with the greatest respect, and by holding their tongues in private. No one ever abused Robert Godwin.

Even the old women did not curse him, as they do in story-books, for they have come to learn — these old women — in the nine- teenth century that curses are as harmless as thistledown. They looked after him as he passed — ^simply folded their arms and looked after him.

His mind, hard set upon the subject in hand, was clear and practical, consequently upon agricultural topics, and such as came within his reach, Godwin could make a good speech. He frequently spoke, express- ing himself in plain and forcible language; his speeches appeared in full in the local

prints, and were even transferred to the London agricultural papers. He possessed a considerable reputation of this kind, and justly so, for he spoke out of the fulness of practical knowledge.

XXIV

then another till the six were gone. He thrust his nostrils into her hand, and pushed her with his face for more. As he moved it brought Robert, who held him, close to Felise. Once again he felt the caress of her dress, even the touch of her arm.

The contrast between them was very marked. Her clear complexion, her golden hair; her form so beautifully shaped that even the loveliness of her face was over- looked. You must forget her form before you could see her features.

His black countenance — black like a piece

of wood that has lain for years in the rain; his colourless eye; his round stout frame ex- pressive of ungraceful strength.

But Ruy, greedy for more apples, would not stand still. Robert lost the touch of her arm, and the caress of her dress. ' He is a fine horse,' said Felise; ' I can- not understand why his owner sold him. Did you not say he wanted money T ' His rent was overdue,' said Robert. At ordinary times he would not have let this out; at the moment he was abstracted from himself to such a degree that his lips an- swered without the consent of his mind. ' His Lady Day rent was overdue — and — and I bought the horse.' ' That he might have the money to pay.' 'Yes.' ' And the price was ?' ' Sixty pounds.' ' I thought you said seventy yesterday.' ' No— did I r

The horse-dealer's instinct had for the

time deserted him. He forgot to add ten pounds to the sum he had really given. ' Is he very much in difficulty ?^ asked Felise, growing bolder. ' I am not sure ' (this was the truth); ' I should like to know.'

Felise was obliged to move, as Ruy worked his face too forcibly against her. She walked with Robert towards the stables, thinking if there was any other leading question she could put. She could not think of another. ' Now may I ask you a favour ?' said Felise, as Robert, having handed Ruy over to the charge of a carter, was returning with her towards the house. 'Certainly.' ' Will you not let old Abner Brown stay in his cottage ? He cannot live very much longer.'

Robert's mental condition stiffened in- stantly. The request brought him back from the glamour into which he had been thrown.

' He has already been there much longer than he ought/ he said. ' I believe it is a year since he ceased to work.' ' Yes — think; he worked up to within one year of eighty-four — surely that should plead for him.' ' I have to consider the estate/ said Robert. ' You know the circumstances — he cannot do any work, nor can his wife; we want the cottage for those who can.' ' But has he not earned a little repose, Mr. Godwin ?' ' He can have it in the workhouse/ ' Do not say so — do not mention that

dreadful place. It would kill the old man to

leave his garden.' ' They will let him sweep up the leaves and weed the paths at the workhouse.' ' He is very, very old, Mr. Godwin; he has lived in that cottage more than forty years, and all the trees in the garden are his own planting — there are apples, and a cherry '

271 ' We want the cottage — we must have it; I know several who will be glad of it/ ' They are no expense/ continued Felise, ' because their son keeps them; let them stay/ ' It is impossible ! as for young Abner, he ought not to live in our cottage and work off the estate/ ' He works for Mr. Goring/ said Felise, beginning to grow angry; but she checked it for the sake of the aged couple. ' Mr. God- win, I will pay you — what is the rent of the cottage ?' ' Two shillings a week.' ' I will pay it, then you will lose nothing/ ' The rent is paid now,' said Godwin. ' You misunderstand; we lose the man's work who should live there.' ' Oh, but they are so old 1' ' There is the workhouse.' ' They will never go there.' ' They must; the parish will not allow out- door relief.'

' Mr. Godwin, do let them stay; I have set my heart upon it/

Who else could have resisted her ? The argument and the trace of anger which had begun to rise had brightened her colour and warmed her whole appearance. Robert re- fused her point-blank. The stored-up passion of so many years, causing an irresistible re- flex action, forced him to oppose her. After this appeal from her, now he knew she wished it, had a sign shone in the heavens still he would not have yielded.

Felise, recognising his stubborn mood, forbore to press further; she spoke for a few minutes with Miss Godwin, and left.

In the afternoon Mr. Goring came home, having consulted his solicitor, who thought that probably there was a right to enclose the spring, as it was on private property, though within a few yards of the highway. The question would be an awkward one; it might cost hundreds of pounds to decide it; he

273

advised his client to have nothing to do with it. • This is indeed a right !' said Mr. Goring ' Time it is that such '' rights" should be abolished — the word itself is reversed in alluding to them. Has any man a '' right," then, to enclose the air, the light ? Doubt- less, if it could be done, there are those who would enclose the ocean and claim it as private property.'

He set out that very evening with Abner to construct a dipping-place in a part of the stream that passed through his little property, intending also to open a footpath to it for the use of the inhabitants.

Felise inquired if he had heard anything in Maasbury about Mr. Barnard's alleged pecuniary difficulties. ' No,' said Goring. ' Why do you wish to know ?' ' There seems so much trouble about us,' replied Felise discreetly. ' So many farmers failing — that is all.

VOL. I. 18

Nor had Mary Shaw discovered anything.

Felise turned over Miss Barnard's Dante scrap-book, wishing the owner would come for it.

Next morning she went over again to God- win's, fed Ruy with apples, petted him and praised him, talked a little whjle with Robert, and begged for old Abner's cottage. In vain.

Four times in succession she visited Ruy, fed him, petted him, stroked him, and seemed more and more loth to leave him.

The fifth morning she did not come; Robert waited and worked with his hands, but she did not come. This was the Satur- day; Sunday he did not think it at all likely she would come. He never slept, nor even attempted to do so on the Saturday or Sun- day night. How he passed them it is diffi- cult to tell, but he constantly moved some- thing or other about with his hands. Two nights without sleep did not leave much trace on his bronze face; but his heart's bitterness

was worn deeper within him, as a storm wears gullies in the rock.

Already, so swift is gossip, the hamlet had begun to talk of Miss Goring and Mr. God- win. Though Felise had helped them in so many ways, though her uncle was actually at that moment working for them, they could not say a good word, they could not credit her with any motive but greed of money. ' She be a-looking after old Godwin's gold.' 'Selling herself to the old miser.' ' Hope his money will choke her.' ' Never thought there was much in her, did you ?'

Such was the tone of their comments.

Felise was disappointed; Miss Barnard had not called for the Dante scrap-book; after her bold effort she seemed no nearer her object. But an idea had been gradually forming itself in her mind, and on Monday she started, always impetuous, to put it into practice.

She went over and fed Ruy once more with apples, Ruy was as greedy of them as

a miser of coin; she talked with Robert, and presently asked him for how much he would sell the horse ? ' Seventy pounds/ said Robert. ' But you only gave sixty for him/ ' I have to make my turn — my profit,' said Robert. ' Will you sell him to me ?' ' Of course.' ' I will buy him,' said Felise. ' You shall have him — seventy pounds.' ' Sixty.' < No— no.' ' Sixty-five.' ' Impossible.' ' Sixty-seven.' ' I couldn't.' ' Sixty-seven — that is seven pounds profit, and all in a few days,' said Felise. ' Seventy pounds,' said Robert decidedly, and Felise saw that it was no use to bar- gain. ' Very well, seventy — I will bring you the

money this evening; you will not part with him to anyone else in the meantime ?' ' Why, no — certainly not.' ' I will come then, this evening/

She returned home, and asked Mr. Goring for the pony-carriage to drive into the town; it was prepared, and she started alone.

So soon as she had left, Robert Godwin said to himself that he had been foolish to part with the horse so easily. She had so set her mind on the horse, he might have asked ninety safely. If he had kept him till the hunting-season some gentleman might have taken a fancy for him and gone still higher, perhaps a hundred and twenty. For the price of a horse is the price of a fancy, and goes up like stocks and shares when buyers are in the vein. Why, very likely she knew of some one who would give her ninety or a hundred for such a horse; very likely that was the secret of her eager- ness to secure him. Robert felt that he had been ' had;' it hurt his semi-professional

pride as a horse-dealer now and then, generally heavily to his gain.

The miser and the lover — despair, hope, and anger — were they not strangely mingled in this man ?

A passionate lover would have given his lady the horse in a moment, especially if as rich as Robert Godwin. With all his riches, and his secret passion, he had but once given her a present. One fair-day — eight years since — for a marvel he spent fourpence (the groat is still a unit in country places) at a stall on ' fairings,' a sort of sweet biscuit, thinking he might see her as he came home. He did see her, and gave her the groat's worth of ' fairings;' the child took them silently, not without some awe of his black face.

He had cleared ten pounds profit, and he was torturing himself because he feared he had missed an opportunity to make twenty.

Yet his hands were never still because of his unmanageable passion — he must work

with them constantly; his heart's bitterness was full to overflowing because he could not have her; the hope her presence gave was like a sword splitting his very heart in two. She stood by him and his lips were dumb — commonplaces are dumbness — his lips were closed with iron-bolts; he could not say one ' word to indicate his meaning, to seek her favour.

Are we cynical moderns right, after all, in our discredit of Fate ? Could there possibly be some fate here, some of that irresistible destiny which in Sophocles carries its tyrant will through generation after generation ? Petty circumstances unregarded lead men on, from step to step, from thought to thought, action to action; is this Fate ?

The greed of the miser; the agony of the lover who knows that he cannot be loved; the pitiless animosity of the tyrant turning by ■ reflex action against the creature of his love; the sharp sword of a hope that only shows what might be zf — these are terrible goads.

fe,WfN!«W#»j|

M

i>w,«w».««'i

g